<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the success of the voyage of the right honourable Heaneage Finch, Earl of Winchilsea, Viscount Maidstone, Baron Fitz-Herbert of Eastwell, Lord of the royal mannor of Wye, Lord Lieutenant of the county of Kent and city of Canterbury, His Majesties ambassadour extraordinary to the high &amp; mighty Prince Sultan Mamet Han, emperour of Turkey, from Smyrna to Constantinople; his arrival there, the manner of his entertainment and audience with the Grand Fizier and Grand Seignior.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30899</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52655)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30899)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1765:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the success of the voyage of the right honourable Heaneage Finch, Earl of Winchilsea, Viscount Maidstone, Baron Fitz-Herbert of Eastwell, Lord of the royal mannor of Wye, Lord Lieutenant of the county of Kent and city of Canterbury, His Majesties ambassadour extraordinary to the high &amp; mighty Prince Sultan Mamet Han, emperour of Turkey, from Smyrna to Constantinople; his arrival there, the manner of his entertainment and audience with the Grand Fizier and Grand Seignior.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by I.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year, 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Winchilsea, Heneage Finch, --  Earl of, d. 1689 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Voyages and travels --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30899:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF The ſucceſs of the voyage of the Right Honourable HENEAGE FINCH, Earl of <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> Vicount <hi>Maidſtone,</hi> Baron <hi>Fitz-Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Eaſtwell,</hi> Lord of the Royal mannor of <hi>Wye,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the County of <hi>Kent</hi> and City of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> His Majeſtjes Ambaſſadour extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to the High &amp; Mighty Prince <hi>Sultan Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met Han,</hi> Emperour of Turkey, from <hi>Smyrna</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> His Arrival there, the manner of his Entertainment and Audience with the <hi>Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier</hi> and <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. R.</hi> in the year, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30899:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30899:2"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the Succeſs of the voyage of his Excellency the Lord <hi>Heneage Finch,</hi> from <hi>Smyrna</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> his arrival there, the manner of his entrance into <hi>Pera,</hi> and of his audience with the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> and <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the ſixt day of <hi>January,</hi> early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, returning aboard with our own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſix Merchants appointed by the Factory of <hi>Smyrna</hi> to attend us; we ſet ſail immediately with the wind at Eaſt, having the <hi>Smyrna</hi> Factour and the Catch in our Company, which arrived with us on New years day. As ſoon as we had ſailed without the command of the Caſtle, it became totally calm, without the leaſt breez or breath of air, which enforced us to caſt our Anchour, and expect untill a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable or a brisker gale did preſent: The next day a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering air from the ſhore at South-eaſt, perſwaded us to weigh our anchours, and ſet our ſails; but this continued no longer than it had brought us out of the Lands protection, and had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30899:3"/>expoſed us to our own arts and the ſtrength of our veſſel, to encounter with thoſe many ſhocks and violences of a ſtorm which ſuddenly enſued: for in a moment the wind altered, coming about to the North-eaſt, ſo that with a ſtrong gale we weathered the Cape <hi>Caliberno,</hi> and ſtanding for the Iſland of <hi>Mitylene,</hi> we intended under the ſhelter of that Land to ſpend our tedious time of the following night. Our Ship lying a drift under her main courſe and fore-ſail by the maſt, the ſtorm by degrees more violently increaſed, that by the morning it was become compleat in all points of its growth and terrour; the Sea was all in a breach, the skie was black and thick, the Sun ſo lowring and red, ſignified the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it: the ſpray of the Sea ſo forcibly carried by the wind over the Ship, that Maſts, Yards, and Decks, were cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a white ſalt. This extremity of weather made us think of ſome port or harbour to ſecure our Ship. The Iſland of <hi>Ipſera</hi> lying South-eaſt eight leagues from <hi>Mitylene,</hi> was ſuppoſed by our Maſter a ſafe place to ſpend the fury of the ſtorm, as having formerly afforded him a kinder entertainment and defence upon the like occaſion of diſtreſſe and fury: Thus ſteering for this Port, our main ſails in the brails and our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail ſet, it was like paper blown away; and bringing another to the yard, it had the misfortune to be foul of the flook of the anchour, and ſo became as unſerviceable as the other: Being thus deprived of the benefit of our commanding ſails, we ſet up our ſprit-ſail and main courſe, ſteering in between the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland <hi>Ipſera</hi> the greater and the leſſe, where keeping too near aloof towards the ſhore, we unfortunately ſtruck upon a rock, which aſtoniſhed us all with a ſtrange amazement; the poor Ship ſtruck five times, endeavouring to clear her ſelf from a totall wrack and ruine, which all of us began to deſpair of; and with caſt up eyes, and ſtretched out arms, thought now of no other but of our laſt and final port: And yet in the midſt of this horrid conſternation and diſtreſſe, it pleaſed God, who was our beſt Pilot, to bring us clear from our rock, with ſome, though (as we hope) with little dammage to our Ship.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30899:3"/>An eſcape ſo miraculous and wonderfull, conſidering the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the ſtorm, the carere and weight of our Ship, as ought to make the 8. day of <hi>January</hi> for ever to be recorded by us to admiration, and anniverſary thankfulneſſe for God's provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and protection: The Ship having thus depth of water again, and come into a place of ſome convenient anchourage, our firſt anchour not holding us, we let fall our ſheet anchour, the <hi>Smyrna</hi> Factour following us. The Catch being again ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated by the night's tempeſt, came not to anchour, and fearing that being not furniſhed with ſo good ground-tackle as we, ſhe was not able to endure and ride out ſo exceſſive a gale; the 8. &amp; 9 day &amp; night the wind continued ſtill violent; the 10 it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to abate, ſo that we could ſend aſhore, and enjoy ſome kind of ſatisfaction, though detained with a contrary wind: The greateſt part of the 12. day proved with little wind, and the 13. a calm, the 14. day between one and two of the clock in the morning, the wind ſprung out of the Weſt South-weſt with an eaſie gale, with which we weighed our anchour and put to the Sea, the wind ſtill continuing favourable and gentle; and the 15. early we came to the Iſland of <hi>Tenedos,</hi> and ſoon after entring the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> paſſing the new Caſtles, from that on the Aſian ſide came off a boat ſent by the Captain of the Caſtle, ſignifying the day before that he had received advice from the <hi>Vizier</hi> that we wereſuddenly to arrive, and that both for our ſelves and Ships that accompanied us, free paſſage ſhould be given without any hinderance or moleſtation: paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing further up the River about five leagues, being about three of the clock in the afternoon of the ſame day, we came up to the Caſtles of <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Abydos:</hi> from the latter, being on the Natolian ſhore, came off a boat with a <hi>Janizarie</hi> and <hi>Drugerman,</hi> to welcome us with Letters from Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> and to return with news of our ſafe arrival: The night following, and likewiſe the 16. day continued there a gentle and favourable gale; ſo that paſſing the Iſland of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora</hi> (about noon of the ſame day) ſcituate at the entrance of the Propontick Sea, formerly called <hi>Proconneſus,</hi> we pleaſantly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30899:4"/>paſſed forward that night, and on the 27. day, being that day three moneths ſince we embarqued in the Downs, we came to an anchor for ſome few hours near the ſeven Towers, until ſuch time as Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> could receive notice of our arrival. And thus giving time for that intelligence, the anchour was again weighed, and we ſtood in for the Port with a freſh gale. Notice being given, that the <hi>Grond Seignior</hi> was ſeated in a Summer-houſe on the corner wall of the <hi>Seraglio:</hi> our Flaggs and Enſigns were diſplayed, our Cuns and Waſtcloths out; and being oppoſite to the point of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> a <hi>Bostangee,</hi> or one belonging to the Gardens of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> came aboard to acquaint us, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s pleaſure was that we ſhould rejoyce with Guns, (for that was his expreſſion) after which were fired 61 Guns, and ſo came to an anchor on <hi>Topa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> ſide, where we received Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> aboard, congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating our ſafe arrival. Againſt next day things were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for our entrance, being the 18. day; and indeed with that handſome State and Equipage, that I believe none of his Predeceſſours, nor yet the Emperours Ambaſſadours, can boaſt of a more honourable, nor a more noble reception. The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> ſent ſeveral of his officers to attend and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him at his firſt landing; and the multitude of people that flocked from all parts, made the buſineſſe of more wonder and expectation. Aſſoon as we deſcended from the Ship into the boat deſigned to carry us aſhore, the Ship fired 51. Guns, with that deliberation, and ſo leiſurely, as continued until his landing; where being met by his own Servants, the Merchants of the place, and thoſe brought with us from <hi>Smyrna;</hi> with the Officers of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> my Lord's Horſe being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Crimſon velvet foot-cloth richly laced, and being mounted thereupon, and his Ladie in the Coach, we marched in this order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The</hi> Vaivod <hi>of</hi> Gallata <hi>and his men.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Captain of the</hi> Janizaries <hi>with his</hi> Janizaries.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>The</hi> Chouſe Baſhaw <hi>with his</hi> Chouſes.</item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30899:4"/>
               <item>4. <hi>The Engliſh Trumpeters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>The Engliſh horſemen, and Merchants.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>My Lord's own Janizaries.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>The Druggermen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>My Lord himſelf with Pages and Footmen by his ſide.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>My Lord's Gentlemen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>His Ladies Coach, and three other Coaches following with her women, made almoſt after the manner of Holland waggons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>The Officers and Reformadoes of the ſhip.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As we marched all the ſtreets were crowded with people, and the windows with ſpectatours, as being unuſual in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crey to ſee a Chriſtian Ambaſſadour attended with ſo many Turkiſh Officers. The preſſe was alſo the more augmented, and the paſſage obſtructed, by caſting 550. five foll. pieces, which My Lord commanded to be diſpoſed of amongſt the people. And thus being arrived at his houſe at <hi>Pera,</hi> he was immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaluted by the Secretary of the Emperours Reſident, in behalf of his Maſter; and ſoon after by the Secretary of the <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimo Ballarino,</hi> and <hi>Capello,</hi> who negotiate the affairs of the Venetian Republique, and the next day by a meſſenger of the French Ambaſſadours, and Dutch Agent. On that day the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> ſent him a preſent of ten ſheep, and fifty hens, a hundred loaves of bread, twenty ſugar loaves, twenty wax candles, a favour extraordinary, not uſually conferred on any Ambaſſadour. On the 20. day of this moneth he had audience of the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> and being attended thither with the ſame ſolemnity as at his firſt entrance; onely that untill he came unto <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſide. He had not the attendance of <hi>Chaus Baſſa</hi> who met him on the other ſide of the water, and thence conducted him to his <hi>Viziers</hi> pallace: At his firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance he was led in between two of his Gentlemen, very few of his retinue being ſuffered to follow him into the preſence of the <hi>Vizier,</hi> who ſate in a little room upon Cuſhions and his feet covered, a fire in the room, and upon a Sapha were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30899:5"/>
               <hi>Baſhaws</hi> and <hi>Chauſes</hi> ſtanding by him: Two Crimſon Velvet ſtools were fetched out; one for my Lord, and the other for Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> on which being ſate, he preſented the Kings Letter to the <hi>Vizier</hi> by the hand of the Chancellor, who was there preſent by him; the Letters were wrote on parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and put in a bagg made of cloth of Gold. As ſoon as they were delivered, my Lord <hi>Bendiſh</hi> began to inform the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier,</hi> that this was that honourable perſon he had formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him was coming Ambaſſadour; rhat he was of that Nobility and Alliance to the King, that had not his Majeſtie highly and in an extraordinary manner intended to honour the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> he would not have expoſed his kinſman to ſo long &amp; dangerous a voyage. Then my Lord began to tell him the Reſtauration of the King, of his greatneſs and power, of his Clemency in pardoning all but ſuch as were engaged in the bloud of his Father; That in his paſſage to this place, he had by the command of the King touched at <hi>Algier,</hi> endeavouring to renew the former articles of peace, and to releaſe an Engliſh Lord which was there a captive, enſlaved contrary to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of peace, but was foiled in the Treaty, and could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to nothing of reaſon or juſtice, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know of the <hi>Vizier</hi> what ſhould be done in this caſe. To which he replied, that he would have a care of it, and ſee to do him juſtice: My Lord further aſſured him of the friendſhip that the King his Maſter deſired to preſerve with the <hi>Grand Seignior;</hi> and therefore deſiring to honour him, hath ſent him his firſt Ambaſſador to ſalute him, before he had appointed or deſigned any for the Chriſtian Princes: To which the <hi>Vizier</hi> proudly replied, that that was but reaſon, ſince the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> was an Emperour and they but Kings, and he the greateſt &amp; moſt Soveraign Potentate of the world. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther told him, that being now come upon a buſineſs of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Complement, he could not inſiſt upon much buſineſs whereby to over burthen him with a tedious diſcourſe, but ſhould referre that to be intimated to him by his Drugerman, at ſome other convenient time of Treaty and diſcourſe. This
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30899:5"/>being paſſed, two bowls of <hi>Sherbet</hi> were brought forth, which we drunk one to another, but not the Turks. This being done, the Engliſh preſent was brought forth and laid before the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier,</hi> conſiſting of twenty Veſts, four of them being of fine Engliſh cloth of ſeveral colours, four Velvet, of ſeveral flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Stuffs of gold and ſilver four, of watered Tabbies four, of ſeveral Sattins worked gaudy and gay after the Turkiſh faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In recompence we received thanks, and my Lord himſelf with Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> and ſix of thoſe that attended were veſted; which veſts had nothing of value more, then that they came from the <hi>Vizier,</hi> as uſual Liveries and Badges of their favours. After this my Lord departed, wearing this paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed veſt untill he came without the gates of the Pallace, and then delivered it to the hands of his Page, and ſo likewiſe did thoſe that followed him to their Servants; and thus in the ſame manner returned back again to his houſe at <hi>Pera,</hi> with an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of fair correſpondencie of a maintainance of the former Capitulations, with an amendment of the afore paſſed abuſes.</p>
            <p>On the 26. <hi>Feb.</hi> my Lord had audience of the <hi>Gr. Seignior,</hi> which was purpoſely deferred until that day of payment of the Janizaries, that ſo the Ambaſſadour might ſee more than an uſual ſolemnity, and make a good report in his own Countrey of the glory and magnificence of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperours. We being attended as formerly when he had audience of the <hi>Vizier,</hi> he departed from his houſe upon the firſt break of day, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſſed the water, was on <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſide met by the Chouſe Baſſaw and his Chouſes, which conducted us to the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> where being entred, and riding through the firſt ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Court we alighted from our horſes, and walked through another Court untill we came to the <hi>Divan,</hi> where at the upper end was placed the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> on his right hand were five other <hi>Viziers,</hi> of which the Captain Baſhaw was one, on his left hand were the two Judges or Chief Juſtices, one of which wore a great Turbant of green, being of the family and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Prophet; near to whom was placed the Toftardar,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30899:6"/>or Lord Treaſurer, with three other Baſhaws, being under Treaſurers. The floor of the Divan was ſpread with Carpets, and on them a rich covering of bags of money to pay the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery, there being in all an hundred and fifty heaps, every one of which conſiſted of ten purſes, and every purſe five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred dollers, ſo that the ſumme by computation amounted to an hundred and fifty thouſand pounds. Being come to the door of the <hi>Divan,</hi> none were admitted in beſides my Lord, Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> and about ſix or ſeven more; being entred, Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> and my Lord approched towards the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier,</hi> others remaining at the lower end of the room; where for them were ſet two ſmall red Velvet Stools, on which being ſet, there paſſed ſome diſcourſe of kindneſſe and civility, which being done, they retired to another part of the room: In the mean while the payment of the Souldiers went forward; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Colonel and Captain receiving the pay of his Regiment and company, which having done, every one of them came up to the <hi>Vizier</hi> and kiſſed the hemme of his veſt on his knees, and ſo retired with great humility, making haſte away from him, paſſing with one ſide towards him, ſo as not to turn his back: The payment being over, three ſmall Tables were brought in (the <hi>Grand vizier</hi> retiring by reaſon of his indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition of body) on which were ſet a large capacious Voider for a Table; that on which they dined being of ſilver oar, other of mixed metal: Being ſet at theſe Tables, their meat was ſerved in one diſh after another, where they had no knives laid for them to cut: for ſuppoſing the ſharpneſs of their ſtomacks would make amends for the want of knives, they fell too after the Turkiſh faſhion and tore it in pieces; but ſcarce was any diſh upon the table, ſometimes almoſt before they had taſted it. but immediately was ſnatched off, and another ſet in his place; having thus ſuperficially proved every diſh, of which there was about two Courſes, the Table was taken away, and the Chouſe Baſhaw adviſed them to accompany him, where they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Honour of the <hi>Grand Seigniors</hi> Veſts, according to the uſual cuſtome upon like occaſions. Eighteen Veſts were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30899:6"/>and one more above the number, as a mark of more honour and favour: Whileſt this was doing, the preſent made to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> by the Turkey Company was diſplayed in open Court, conſiſting of fifty Veſts, ten being of Velvet, ten of Sattin, ten of Cloth of Gold, ten of Tabbies, ten of fine Engliſh cloth; every one of which Veſts was held by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſon, ſo that fifty men were rancked in order for the better appearance, and four Engliſh Maſtiffs were alſo given as an addition to the Preſent. In this Court were alſo drawn up the whole body of the Janizaries that were then paid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of five thouſand men, amongſt whom there was that ſilence, that not one whiſper or noiſe, or the leaſt motion was underſtood: And as the Janizaries Aga and other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders paſſed, the bowing and ſalutations that they made were alſo regular at the ſame time, as may well teſtifie the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſſe of the Diſcipline and admirable obedience, which hath been the ſole cauſe of their Conqueſt and enlargement of their Empire. Being thus veſted, and the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> gone into the preſence of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> to whom we bowed as he paſſed, two Cappagee Baſhaws with Silver ſtaves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted him to the Audience, none being permitted to follow him, but Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> his Brother the Drugerman, the Captain of the Ship, the Treaſurer, and his Secretary, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Cloth of Cold bagg, in which were the Kings Letters. The Gate we firſt entred was ſet vvide open, vvithin it vvas paved vvith vvhite Marble, vvhere attended ſome fourty Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs, all clothed vvith divers Colours of ſilk and Sattin Veſts, coming near the Preſence door, vve made a ſtand in the Porch, vvhere runnes a pleaſant Fountain of vvater, and trode very ſoftly, ſo as not to diſturb vvith the leaſt motion that great Majeſty, vvhere vvas ſo profound a ſilence, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vvas heard more than the murmuring of the Fountain: Juſt at the Entrance hung a Ball of gold ſtudded vvith Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds and precious ſtones, and about it great Chains of rich Peail. The Chamber vvhere the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> ſate, vvas covered vvith a Carpet of Crimſon Velvet, and embroidered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30899:7"/>vvith Gold vvire; and ſo likevviſe vvas an open Gallery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Entrance, through vvhich vve firſt paſſed, and many of them beſet vvith ſmall ſeed-pearl. The <hi>Grand Seigntor</hi> himſelf ſate in a Throne raiſed a ſmall heighth from the ground, ſupported vvith four pillars plated vvith Gold, from the top hung great Balls of maſſie and vveighty Gold: The Cuſhions he ſate upon, and thoſe alſo that lay by, and the Carpets ſpread upon the Throne were all beſet vvith Jevvels; on his Right hand ſtood the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> the tvvo Cappagee Baſhavvs took him by each hand and brought him into the Preſence, about the middle of the room, laying their hands upon his head, made him bovv untill he had almoſt touched the Carpets vvith his fore-head, and then raiſing him again, they retired vvith him backvvard unto the furtheſt part of the room; in like manner they did unto the reſt of his company. The Kings Letters being preſented, they vvere appointed to be carried to the Lord Chancellour, and the Drugerman by his order in the Turkiſh Language, read in his Paper to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Firſt declaring hovv the King of <hi>England</hi> vvas reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red again vvithout War or any Conditions, and the great Clemency of the King in pardoning all, but ſuch as had a hand in the murther of his Father. Secondly, to recommend to his Majeſty the continuance of his protection to our Merchants. Thirdly, to beg all Engliſh ſlaves, as a Teſtimony of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties gracious acceptance of him. The Ceremonies being over, and the paper read, vve immediately retired avvay; and ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing along by the Janizaries unto our horſes, and being mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vve ſtood out of the vvay to ſee thoſe Souldiers march by us, vvhich indeed ſeemed a very flouriſhing Militia of young men, ſtrong and vvell cloathed; about tvvo or three thouſand firſt marched vvith baggs of money upon their ſhoulders, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards follovved about as many more running vvith much haſte after the money, next follovved their Commanders vvell mounted, vvith brave feathers of a yard high upon-their heads; next follovved the Chouſes and their Commanders, vvith ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Baſhavvs of great quality. Laſt of all the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30899:7"/>vvho being gone, my Lord and his attendance proceeded for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards, and ſo returned to his houſe. It is obſervable, that there vvere admitted to eat in the Divan many of his Retinue, vvhich never before vvas admitted, onely for the tvvo Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours; and alſo that none had acceſs to the preſence of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> but onely the tvvo Ambaſſadours and the Drugerman: 'Tis obſervable, that the diſhes in vvhich the meat vvas ſerved up vvere of a greeniſh colour, made of earth very ordinary to the eye, yet ſuch as Coſt the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> an hundred and fifty dollers apiece, brought from <hi>China;</hi> vvhoſe virtue is ſuch, that as ſoon as any poyſon comes into them they break immediately, and therefore the moſt neceſſary for the ſecurity of the Emperour.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
